<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pages>

    <page>
        <category>reminder</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>Selecting a course for today</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>The Sailing Committee has recommended courses for each of the cardinal wind directions. The
                courses also include options for light winds and low tide conditions. Each course is shown as it
                should be displayed on the course board and has some tips on how to position the inflatable buoys.
            </p>

            <p>The courses can be viewed by selecting the CourseFinder option on the Status Page</p>

            <!-- p>A paper copy of the course guide should be on the OOD desk in the race box -
                <a href="https://www.starcrossyc.org.uk/racing/apps/course-guide" target="_blank">there is an online
                    version here
                </a>
            </p -->
            <p>An online copy of the buoy locations <a
                    href="https://www.starcrossyc.org.uk/racing/essentials/buoy-chart" target="_blank">can be found here
            </a>
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
        <p>As OOD you are of course free to come up with your own race course - but in this case please check your course with a member of the Sailing Committee</p>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>reminder</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>Some reminders on running a pursuit race</question>
        <answer>TO BE COMPLETED</answer>
        <notes></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>reminder</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>6</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>Managing Multiple Races</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>Some suggestions if you are scheduled to run more than one race in a day at Starcross YC.
            <p>
            <p>First of all when setting the course for the first race - consider what changes you will make to the
                course for subsequent races to keep it interesting for the competitors. It is generally relatively easy
                to adjust the amount of running / broad reaching /and close reaching by simply changing a single buoy or
                alternatively moving the inflatable buoys. Making these small changes will make it fairer for all types
                of boat racing.
            </p>
            <p>Organise a briefing for competitors before the first race. Explain the following:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>you will try to turn around the races quickly - the aim will be that the warning signal for the
                    second race will be made within 5 minutes of the last boat finishing the first race. If this is not
                    possible a postponement will be signalled - the postponement will be cancelled no less than 3
                    minutes before the warning signal for the first start.
                </li>
                <li>you will likely change the course between races - watch for Flag C and a sound signal</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                <b>FIRST RACE</b> - run this as usual - selecting the relevant race on the raceManager racebox PROGRAMME page. Do not let
                this race overrun and be ready to shorten course as necessary. While the final few boats are finishing -
                ask the safety boats to adjust the course for the second race.
            </p>
            <p>
            Once all the boats have finished, PUBLISH the results (on the results page) even if there are still some
                issues to resolve (this has the effect of taking a backup ciopy of all the results for safety). Take
                note of any outstanding issues - but leave them until all the races are complete. Do NOT close the race
                at this stage.
            </p>
            <p>
                <b>SECOND RACE</b> - go back to the PROGRAMME page (click the green text on the left hand side of the top
                 navigation bar) and select the second race and run it as normal. To restart the lights
                box turn the power off for 30 seconds and then power on. You can now start the race as usual. Once all
                the boats have finished this race, PUBLISH the results but do NOT close the race
            </p>
            <p>Now return to the racebox PROGRAMME page and select the first race again. Resolve any outstanding
                issues with the results for this race and republish if necessary. You can now CLOSE this race. Repeat
                the process for race 2.
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Note: leaving outstanding results issues until all races have been completed takes the pressure off the OOD
                team trying to sort out the result for Race 1 while starting Race 2. Publishing the interim results
                immediately after each race is complete - before correcting any issues - has the effect of creating a
                safety backup of the data. It is a good idea to select "no upload to the website" when you select the
                interim publishing option.
            </p>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>pickrace</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>0</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>what is the PROGRAMME page for?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This page presents the race(s) to be run today and allows you to pick the race you want to deal with. To
                access the race just click the <b>RUN RACE</b> button and it will be presented in the browser window.
            </p>
            <p>To switch to another race from within raceManager - you can go back to this page by clicking the green <b>
                racebox: “racename”
            </b> link at the top left of each page. To go back to the race click the <b>BACK TO RACE</b> button.
            </p>
            <p>To check the format of any race on today’s programme - click the black ‘list’ icon within the relevant
                race display.
            </p>
            <p>If the race you want to run is not shown then you can use the <b>ADD NEW RACE</b> button to add the race
                to the raceManager system.
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Note:<p></p>At Starcross YC it will be <u>very unusual</u> if you need to add a new race to the programme
                - probably worth checking with a member of the Sailing Committee before you do this
            </p>
            ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>pickrace</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>Where can I find the Sailing Instructions?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>The Starcross YC Sailing Instructions for club racing can be found on the club website <a
                href="https://www.starcrossyc.org.uk/racing/essentials/sailing-instructions-v3" target="_BLANK">on this
            page
        </a>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>If you are running an event open to non-club members then it may have specific sailing instructions which
            may be found on the SYC events page <a href="https://www.starcrossyc.org.uk/open-events" target="_BLANK">on
            this page
        </a>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>race</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>0</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>what is the STATUS page for?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This page gives you information on the race you are about to run - specifically the race format (start
                sequence, signals etc.). It also allows you to change some details (e.g. name of race officer)
            </p>
            <p>It also allows you to:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Set the number of laps for each fleet</li>
                <li>Send an email to the team responsible for managing your raceManager system</li>
                <li>Mark the race as ABANDONED or CANCELLED</li>
                <li>CLOSE the race when you have accounted for all competitors</li>
                <li>RESET the entire race if you want to start again</li>
            </ul>
            <p>You will normally use this page at the beginning of your race officer duty to check the race format and
                set laps - and at the end of the race to indicate if it was abandoned / cancelled or to close a
                successfully completed race. You might also wish to send a message to the raceManager team to explain
                any problems you had with the software or issues with the results.</p>
            ]]></answer>
        <notes></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>race</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>how do I reset a race?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>If you really want to start the entire race again in raceManager there is a reset option on the STATUS
                page. Click the
                RESET button and then enter the confirmation word and click the submit button to activate the reset
            </p>
            <p>You will lose all the entries and laptimes that you have entered. However if you are using the SAILOR
                application for collecting entries these will still be available for you to reenter in the normal
                way.
            </p>

        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>
                <b>DO NOT USE THIS APPROACH if you have already started a fleet</b>
                - if you still want to start the entire race again do the following, signal abandonment (instruct the
                Safety Boats to
                inform the competitors) and
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>stop the start sequence on the lights box (power off the lights box and then on again)</li>
                <li>signal abandonment - red and orange beacons (instruct the Safety Boats to inform the competitors)
                </li>
                <li>use the raceManager RESET button as described above - then reload entries</li>
                <li>change the course if necessary - use Flag C + two sound signals</li>
                <li>restart the start sequence on the lights system and on raceManager - and run the rest of the race as
                    normal
                </li>
            </ul>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>race,timer,results</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>10</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>how do I ABANDON a race?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>You can abandon a race at any time from the STATUS page - just click the Abandon button. You can also change
                your mind and unabandon the race as long as you continued to record lap times
            </p>
            <p>Once the race is abandoned you can then CLOSE the race - do NOT publish the partial results.</p>
        </answer>
        <p>
            <b>IMPORTANT ... at Starcross YC our Sailing Instructions allow us to CURTAIL a club race rather than
                abandon it.
            </b>
        </p>
        <p>You SHOULD use this approach if all the boats still racing in a fleet have finished at least one lap as
            this allows us to salvage a race result from a race that would otherwise be lost. It is most often used
            if the wind dies to nothing towards the end of a race. To CURTAIL a race go to the results page and
            use the Change Finish Lap option - this will have the following effect:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>average lap racing: set the finish lap to the last one that the leading boat in the fleet
                completed
            </li>
            <li>handicap/class racing: set the finish lap to the one that all boats in the fleet have completed</li>
        </ul>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
        <p>Note: This function can also be useful if you have forgotten to shorten the race in raceManager, but have
            signalled a finish to competitors. Simply set the finish lap to the shortened number of laps.</p>
            ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>entries</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>0</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>what is the ENTRIES page for?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This page allows you to enter boats into the race and manage the entries.</p>
            <p>If you are using the sailor signon system in raceManager then you can use the LOAD ENTRIES button to load
                everybody who signs on. When the button flashes red it means that there are some entries waiting to be
                loaded.
            </p>
            <p>Alternatively you can use the ENTER BOATS button to search the database for boats to enter. You can
                search for the sail number, class name, or helms surname. The system will find all matches in the
                database and then you can select the boats to enter.
            </p>
            <p>The entries will be shown for each fleet as a separate tab - click the tab to see a fleet entries. You
                can edit an entry - changing the crew, sail number, or handicap for this race only. You can also mark a
                competitor for doing a club duty - they will be allocated points for the race according to the way your
                raceManager system is configured.
            </p>
            <p>If you have new boats (i.e not in the database), or a new class of boat you should use the REGISTER NEW
                CLASS and/or REGISTER NEW BOAT buttons to add the details to the database. Once in the database you can
                enter them in the normal way.
            </p>
            <p>Finally you can use the PRINT ENTRIES button to get a list of entries in a variety of formats.</p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Note:<p></p>When you press the timer start button on the START page it will collect any late entries from
                the sailor signon system automatically.
            </p>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>entries</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>I cannot find the boat I want to enter</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This generally only occurs if your club does not use the raceManager SAILOR application to allow the
                competitor to create their own entry or if you hae a new competitor that unfamiliar with the SAILOR application.
            </p>

            <p>The Enter Boat button on the ENTRIES page allows you to search using sail number, class name, or helm
                surname. If you cannot find the boat you are looking for it is probably because it is not in the
                raceManager database. In this case you will need to add the new boat using the Register New Boat button
                - just fill in the form.
            </p>
            <p>Important - after registering the new boat you will still need to use the Enter Boat button to enter it in the normal
                way.
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>In very rare cases you may have a new boat which belongs to a class that is not recognised by raceManager.
                In this case use the Register Class button first to create the new class. Then use he Register New Boat
                button to create the new boat in the new class, and finally use the Enter Boat button to ener it into
                the race.
            </p>
            ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>start</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>0</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>what is the START page for?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This page is used to start the race timer and manage the start sequence.</p>
            <p>Use the START TIMER button to start the raceManager clock at the same time as you make the first WARNING
                signal (e.g. 6 minute gun) for the first fleet in the start sequence. This will start the master
                countdown clock - and the individual fleet start countdowns. Once the countdowns to each start is
                complete the clocks will show the elapsed time for each fleet.
            </p>
            <p>If you want to stop the clock and reset the start sequence (e.g if you decide to change the course) -
                click the Timer button again (it will ask you to confirm the action by typing “stop”).
            </p>
            <p>30 seconds before each fleet starts the “Start Infringements” and “General Recall” buttons will be
                enabled. Use the START INFRINGEMENTS button to record start line infringements such as OCS, DNS, DNC
                etc.. If you decide to have a general recall use the GENERAL RECALL button to enter the wall clock time
                for the actual start time of the fleet in question</p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Note:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>If you forget to start the Timer when you begin the flags/lights start sequence - use the “Forgot to
                    start the timer” button. This will allow you to enter the wall clock time that you actually began
                    the start sequence.
                </li>
                <li>The timer displays for each fleet will flash 30 seconds before each start to alert you to an
                    upcoming start .
                </li>
            </ul>
            ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>start</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>I forgot to start the Timer</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This is a relatively common mistake.</p>
            <p>use the "Forgot to Start Timer" button on the TIMER page. This will allow you to enter the clock time
                (hh:mm:ss) for the time you should have started the timer - i.e. the time you made the first signal in
                the start sequence.
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Obviously you should try to input an accurate time for the first signal - but it does not need to be
                accurate to within a few seconds - small errors are unlikely to have a significant impact on the results.
            </p>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>start</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>10</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>How do I handle a general recall?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>If you signal a general recall for a fleet - that fleet must restart after remaining fleets have
                started.   Use the following procedure:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>restart the lights system (power off / power on) - set the number of starts to 1 (or however many fleets you have recalled)</li>
                <li>start the recalled start sequence on the light box (take a note of the time of the warning signal</li>
                <li>if you want to use the black flag - hoist at the 3 minute sound signal</li>
                <li>on the START page in raceManager click the General Recall option for the fleet(s) in question - enter the clocktime (hh:mm:ss) of the start gun for the recalled fleet (i.e. the time you notes + 6 minutes)</li>
                <li>. . . continue to run the race as normal</li>
            </ul>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>timer</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>0</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>what is the TIMER page for?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This is the page where you record lap times for each boat - and you will spend most of the race on this
                page.
            </p>
            <p>The default display uses the Tabbed fleet organisation - click the relevant tab to view a fleet. To time
                a lap - just click the watch next to the relevant boat and the lap time will appear. Colour shading is
                used to indicate which boats are no longer racing, or on their last lap, or finished.
            </p>
            <p>You can also do the following for each boat:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Delete (UNDO) the last lap time recorded</li>
                <li>Set a scoring code (e.g. DNF, NSC etc.)</li>
                <li>Edit the lap times</li>
                <li>Add the boat to the ‘bunch’ list to help manage</li>
                <li>Finish the boat at a lap other than the finish lap - average lap racing only.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>To shorten the course for one fleet - click the blue button above the list of boats - the race will then
                finish on the next lap. Alternatively you can click the SHORTEN ALL FLEETS button on the right of the
                page. This will shorten all fleets at their next lap.
            </p>
            <p>If you have many fleets and many competitors you may benefit from using one of the alternative TIMER
                views - click the CHANGE VIEW option on the black menu bar. This will then give you the option of
                condensed views which will allow you to see all boats racing without having to scroll or change tabs.
                The three condensed views are organised by:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>Sail Number</b>
                    - best option for lots of boats (50+)
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Class</b>
                    - best option if you have relatively few classes
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Fleet</b>
                    - best option if fleets tend not to be mixed up on the race course
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>Most of the functions of the tabbed display are available. Time laps by clicking the relevant boat button
                - or use the gear wheel menu to get the other functions. You can switch between the different views at
                any time. If you have relatively few classes the class view is probably the best option.</p>
            ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Note:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>The BUNCH facility is very useful to deal with groups of boats crossing the line in a bunch -
                    further details are available in the separate help topic
                    <b>“how do I use the BUNCH facility?”</b>
                </li>
            </ul>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>timer</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>5</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>I forgot to Shorten the course?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>It is a common mistake to signal a shortened course but forget to shorten the course in raceManager. You
                signal the boats finish with the hooter, but they are not finished by raceManager
            </p>
            <p>This can easily be corrected after the race. On the RESULTS page find the "Change Finish Lap" function on
                the right hand side of the screen. Click this and it will show the finish lap set for each fleet. Simply
                set the actual finish lap for the fleet(s) you forgot to shorten and raceManager will automatically set
                the boats to finished.
            </p>
            <p>For example if you had originally set the finish lap for fleet 1 to lap 4, but actually finished the
                boats on lap 3 - just change the finish lap to 3.
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>timer</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>10</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>How do I correct a lap time?</question>
        <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>On the TIMER page - using the TABBED view find the boat for which you want to make the correction.
                Click the edit icon (pencil) and the lap times recorded for that boat will be shown. Edit the incorrect
                lap times by entering the correct elapsed time in hh:mm:ss format.
            </p>
            <p>When you have completed the corrections - click the Update Lap Times button to apply them.</p>
            <p>If you want to add a missed lap - just click the boat record to get a new lap - then use the edit button
                again to make the relevant corrections to each lap.
            </p>
        ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>If the error you want to correct is a finishing time (i.e. for a boat on the last lap) - the edit function on the
                RESULTS page provides a more comprehensive mechanism to correct this time and make other changes (e.g. no. of laps, apply
                penalty points, change PY number, add crew name etc.)
            </p>
        ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
        <category>pursuit</category>
        <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
        <rank>0</rank>
        <active>1</active>
        <question>what is the PURSUIT page for?</question>
        <answer>TO BE COMPLETED</answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
    <category>results</category>
    <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
    <rank>0</rank>
    <active>1</active>
    <question>what is the RESULTS page for?</question>
    <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>This page allows you to check the race results and correct any mistakes, before publishing them . Once
                published you can print the race results (and updated series results where relevant). The results will
                also be made available on the club website.
            </p>
            <p>The results for each fleet are accessed in the normal way using the relevant tab at the top of the page.
                The tabs include an indication of whether the results are complete or have problems that need resolving
                (normally one or more boats who haven’t been finished or given a scoring code such as DNF). When you
                click a fleet tab the system, when relevant, will present a list of possible problems with the results.
            </p>
            <p>You can correct the results - setting scoring codes and using the edit option to update details about the
                competitor and their finishing time and no. of laps completed.
            </p>
            <p>Once you are happy the results are complete and correct - use the PUBLISH button to produce the results
                files that you can print and will be automatically posted to the club website. As part of this process
                you will need to add information on the wind conditions during the race and select some options for the
                results process.</p>
            ]]></answer>
    <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Note:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You can correct and publish the results multiple times as necessary until the race is CLOSED on the
                    status page.
                </li>
                <li>You can publish the results even if there are still outstanding warnings - but the results files
                    will not be posted to the website - use the REPORT ISSUE button to send a message to your
                    raceManager team.
                </li>
                <li>If you want to correct any of the lap times other than the finishing lap go to the TIMER page and
                    use the edit option for the competitor in question.
                </li>
                <li>The results page gives you an option to change the lap used to finish each fleet - this can be
                    useful if you signalled a shortened course and finished the boats, but forgot to record that
                    shortened course in raceManager. Further details are provided in the separate help topic “I forgot
                    to shorten the course”.
                </li>
            </ul>
            ]]></notes>
    </page>

    <page>
    <category>timer</category>
    <author>Mark Elkington - SYC</author>
    <rank>2</rank>
    <active>1</active>
    <question>how do I use the BUNCH function ?</question>
    <answer><![CDATA[
            <p>The recommended approach for using raceManager to record lap and finish times is to use the BUNCH
                function on the timer page - ESPECIALLY if the race has more than 20 boats.  </p>
            <br>
            <p>With this approach - one person 'spots' boats approaching  the  line when they are 200 - 300 m away.
                The person running raceManager clicks the blue button (with a pin icon) for each boat spotted and
                they will then appear in a list on the right hand side of the screen.</p>
            <br>
            <p>You can now use this 'approaching boat' list to easily and quickly record them as they cross the line
                - avoiding the panic of finding them in the few seconds as they cross the line.</p>
            <br>
            <p>The bunch list has up/down arrows so that you can adjust the likely order that the boats will cross
                the line to make it even easier.  You can also remove boats from the bunch list using the red delete icon.</p>
            ]]></answer>
        <notes><![CDATA[
            <p>Most OODs who have tried this feature find it MUCH easier and less stressful - give it a try.</p>
            ]]></notes>
    </page>

</pages>


